<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Spectacle for vsurers and succors of poore folkes bloud whereby they may see, Gods iust dislike and reuenge, vpon their vncharitable and vnciuill oppression, with a horrible murther committed by a young man, that hanged his owne mother in August last, 1606.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23030.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23155486</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23155486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26311</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26311)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1781:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Spectacle for vsurers and succors of poore folkes bloud whereby they may see, Gods iust dislike and reuenge, vpon their vncharitable and vnciuill oppression, with a horrible murther committed by a young man, that hanged his owne mother in August last, 1606.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Wright, and are to be sold at his shop neere Christs-Church gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³.</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains illustration.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Avarice --  Moral and ethical aspects.</term>
               <term>Youth --  Conduct of life.</term>
               <term>Parenting --  Moral and ethical aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26311:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 106 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26311:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 106 -->
            <p>A Spectacle for Vſurers and <hi>Succers of poore folkes bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby they may ſee, Gods iuſt diſlike <hi>and reuenge, vpon their vncharitable and Vnciuill oppreſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a horrible murther committed by a young man, that hanged his owne Mother in Auguſt laſt. 1606.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of usurer being devoured by rats</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for Iohn Wright, and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere Chriſts-Church gate. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise_on_usury">
            <pb facs="tcp:26311:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26311:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
            <head>A true treatiſe, declaring how mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly an Vſurer was deuoured by Rats, at <hi>Charret</hi> neere to the citty of <hi>Aix</hi> in <hi>Prouence,</hi> within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>France,</hi> on the ſecond day of Auguſt. 1606.</head>
            <head type="sub">According to the <hi>French</hi> Copie, printed at <hi>Lions,</hi> by <hi>Leger Bonhomme.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>H, what a world is this, when we muſt haue amongeſt vs, who are baptiſed in the name of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and doe carry the names of Chriſtians, men ſo voyde of all charity, and ſo without all huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity towards their neighbours, that they are not aſhamed by all forts of greedy couetouſneſſe and extortions, as by vnreaſonable enhaunſing the price of victualls, and all other cruell and vnkind meanes, to oppreſſe and vtterly vndoe their poore Chriſtian brethren and ſiſters, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe or pitty to the fatherleſſe children, or diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed widowes, as I may ſay, that we ſeeme rather to liue among Jewes, than Chriſtians? Yea, it may be auouched, that the Turkes and Saracins, I had almoſt ſaid, the very ſauage and brutiſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericanes, would be aſhamed to plot and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſuch horrible and accurſed meanes, for the ſpoyling and pining of poore Chriſtians, as is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed among vs, who make, profeſſion to haue beene trayned in Chriſt his ſchoole. Which might iuſtly make to bluſh for ſhame our Vſurers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26311:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->and vnſatiable greedy minded men, who care for nothing but inriching themſelues: although it be with the ruine and vtter vndoing of infinite poore people, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſuffer, yea cauſe to periſh. Whoſe cries vndoubtedly do aſcend vnto theeares of the Lord, and he being a iuſt Iudge, will be auenged thereon. And though he puniſh not viſibly in this life alwayes the vnmercifulneſſe of wicked world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: yet hath he ſundry times ſhewed fearefull tokens of his diſpleaſure againſt ſuch dealings: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which, marke this notable example fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>Vpon the ſecond day of Auguſt laſt paſt, in the yeare of Grace <hi>1606,</hi> at <hi>Charret,</hi> a little towne nere to the Citty of <hi>Aix</hi> in <hi>Prouence,</hi> within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>France,</hi> there dwelt a rich Vſurer, named <hi>George Rolet,</hi> of the age of about fifty yeares. Hee had three Graniers full of Corne, and two cellars full of wine, and much cattell of his owne, feeding on both ſides of <hi>Aix:</hi> beſides great ſtore of money that was owing him. And he neuerlent any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or money worth, to any, without ſufficient pawnes, or elſe to men that were wealthy. And he ſo dealt by lending, as euery ſix moneths he would commonly double his principall: ſo vngraciouſly had he hardened his heart by wicked vſuryes and extortions to inrich himſelfe.</p>
            <p>His wife was dead, hauing left him no childe neyther had he any body, for whom he might thus miſerably ſtrape theſe goods together, but one Neece: for to inrich whom, and to fulfill his owne vnſatiable couetouſneſſe, hee omitted no vile,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26311:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->and abhominable practiſes of vſury vnaſſaied, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer regarding how wretchedly his ſoule were left quite abandoned of charity and al piety, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it became a bondſlaue to the Deuill, who as a hangman or executioner of Gods iuſt wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked, pay thoſe their hire in the ende, that are ruled by him.</p>
            <p>Now it ſo fel out, that this wretched Vſurer had not ſold any of his corne or wine that yeare, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vntill a time ſhould come when he might ſell it deerer. but when he ſaw the yeare ſo farre paſt, as he could hope for no greater price, he thought it beſt to ſet open his Graniers, and to ſell his corne: which he did vpon a Market day. And forthwith came haſting thether, manye people of ſundry ſexes &amp; ages, for to buy Corne. Amongſt others came a poore woman a Widow, from a Village called <hi>Montalien,</hi> beeing a little league diſtant from thence. The womans name was <hi>Claudia Balme:</hi> who meaning to buy corne, aſked him, how hee ſold a buſhell? He anſwered, fiue ſhillings. What (ſayd ſhe) fiue ſhillings? Now that God beſtoweth ſuch plenty on vs, you might wel affoard it for three ſhillings. I had rather (ſayd he) be eaten vp with Rats, then I would let it go for leſſe then fiue.</p>
            <p>There withall, at the ſame inſtant, comes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poore woman, from another Village not far off, called Werre in, to whom this Vſurer had lent foure crownes-worth of cor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, vppon condition, that ſhe muſt pay him a third partmore then the price of the Market, and beſides, to pay ſix pence a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26311:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->moneth vſury for euery crowne: for aſſiſtance whereof, he had receyued of the ſayd woman, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Margaret Paſchall,</hi> ſeuen rings in pawne. This foreſaid day, came the ſaid <hi>Margaret Paſchall,</hi> and ſayd vnto him, Mayſter <hi>George Rolet,</hi> I haue brought you the money which I owe you, and I pray you giue mee my rings againe, He anſwered her, yes Goſſip, you ſhall. Then ſhe telling him out firſt the principall, and then the intereſt, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth agayne ver rings. The Vſurer taketh her money and locketh it vp, &amp; opening a cupbord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out a folded paper, and deliuereth it vnto her, ſaying: Lo Goſſip, there be your goodes. She o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the paper, ands one of her rings wanting, where at being much grieued, ſhe ſayd vnto him. I haue payd you your full aſking. and yet I miſſe here one of my rings: I beſeech you deale not ſo hardly with met, as to keepe it, but let me haue it agayne. He denyed, that he had any mo of her then the ſixe. The woman, contrariwiſe auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that ſhee had deliuered to him ſeuen, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing vnto him what manner of one it was, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it was the firſt that euer her deceaſſed huſband had giuen her. He ſtill denyed it. The poore woman fell on weeping, and ſtill affirmed, that he had her ſayd ring. Hee after many other oathes and proteſtations, did in the ende (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his vſuall manner of ſwearing, or rather of curſing himſelfe) beſeech God, for to ſuffer the Rats to eate and deuour him vp, if euer he had, or receiued any ſuch ring. This poore woman ſel on her knees, ſaying: I pray and moſt humbly beſeech
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26311:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->God Almighty, that it may ſo come to paſſe, and that he ſhew ſome wonderfull token vpon you or mee, to make manifeſt whether of vs doo ſweare falſly: and I verily truſt, that God who is moſt iuſt, will declare miraculouſly, which of vs holdeth the trueth, and which the contrary.</p>
            <p>She had ſcarce made an ende of her prayer, but immediatly there came (a wonderfull thing to teh an innumerable ſort of Rats, which ſet vpon this Vſurer, ſome on one part of him, ſome on another. And albeit his ſeruants ſought by all meanes to driue them a way, they laboured in vaine: for the more they hunted them away, the mo in multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes came ſtill, more and more aſſayling him.</p>
            <p>His friends and kinſfolke cauſed him to bee ſtripped, and ſo to bee wrapped in a cleane cloth, and to be carried a way into another lodging. But he was no ſooner brought thether, but theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min Rats (as iuſt executors of Gods will) came running thether in flockes, and gnawed his body, who had miſerably ſucked, gnawed and deuoured the goods of very many poore people. And apply what remedies thoſe that were about him could doe by any meanes, yet could they not ſtay theſe Rats, but that in twenty &amp; foure houres they had depriued him of his life. So he died the ſecond of Auguſt, in the yeare of our Lord <hi>1606.</hi> about foure of the clocke in the afternoone. His friends and kinſfolke thought to make ſome funerall or bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of the remainder of his body, which theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle creatures had left: whereof they were decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for before midnight, they had ſcarfe left him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26311:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->the leaſt ſhew of a body, but had carried all away: ſo as no man can tell what became thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus may wee learne by this wicked mans miſerable ende, that wee are not created for our ſelues alone, but to be helpers and comforters one to another: and that we ought not by vſury, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and ſuch vniuſt meanes, to catch away, from others vncharitably and vnconſcionably, that which is not our owne. And much leſſe, that we ſhould in any wiſe ſweare by his name raſhly and falſely, who is a iuſt iudge and almighty. Neyther to curſe our ſelues but rather to pray for Gods dayly bleſſing. God for his mercyes ſake amend vs all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_matricide">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26311:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
            <head>A Treatiſe moſt true, of a curſed young youth of <hi>Remilly</hi> in <hi>Sauoy,</hi> who miſerably and ſhamefully ſtrangled and hanged his owne mother.</head>
            <head type="sub">With his puniſhment for the ſame, on Satterday the <hi>19.</hi> of Auguſt. <hi>1606.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>According to the <hi>French</hi> Copie printed at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> by <hi>Peter Chantenefue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithſtanding that the cruell murther, committed by that firſt murtherer <hi>Cain</hi> on the perſon of his brother, be left vnto all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes mentioned, as a haynous wickedneſſe much diſpleaſing to God, and abhominable before men: yet haue there beene ſome found ſo inhumane and cruell, as they haue imitated, if not ſurpaſſed him in ſuch villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Nero,</hi> who moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally cauſed his owne mother to bee ſlaine, and her wombe to be ripped vp, that he might ſee the place where he lay during the time that his mother bare him? And not much leſſe deteſtably performed, will this treatiſe ſhewe a parricide.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Remilly,</hi> a little towne of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> there dwelt a woman named <hi>Gaſparde Briſin,</hi> widow to one <hi>Anthony Moillon</hi> deceaſſed, and ſhe had a ſonne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>George Moillon,</hi> now come to the age of neere twenty yeares. Her deceaſſed huſband, knowing her to be a thrifty howſwife, had by will certayne yeeres before, left her miſtreſſe and gouerneſſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26311:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->all his goods, without yeelding account thereof to any, before her ſonne were come to the age of twenty yeares: and then, if ſhe and he did not like to dwell together any longer, ſhe to haue her part of the land, with halfe of the goods, and a thouſand Florins ouerplus.</p>
            <p>The ſonne now ſeeing himſelfe almoſt twenty yeeres old, kept ruffian like &amp; diſordered company, which is too co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon a thing now a dayes. He then muſt haunt tauerns, play, dance, and ryot luſtily. The mother, on the other ſide ſought to bridle this young colt, and would not let him haue too much money, for feare hee ſhould ſpoile himſelfe, with voluptuouſnes.</p>
            <p>He ſtill was vrged by thoſe that kept him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to force his mother to feede him with money, or elſe to ſel her yarne, linnen cloth, plate, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe he could catch, &amp; to make money therof. He, as pliable as waxe, to take any impreſſion, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their counſayle, was dayly at his mother for money. She, (though hardly) would now and then giue him a little: which not ſo ſoone receiued, but it was preſently ſpent. He then commeth for more, which not obtayning, he falls to threatning and to offer fowle ſpeeches vnto her.</p>
            <p>At whitſontide laſt, the wake being at that place then when many youthes ſhould aſſemble, this yong man, among all other, would bee ſtored with money &amp; ſpend prodigally among his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions, tooke ſixe of the beſt wether ſheepe that were in his mothers paſture, and ſold them to the butcher. Then during the merriment, who but hee at dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, banketting and play: ſo as the laſt of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26311:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->three holidaies he had not a penny left him of ſixe crownes that he had receiued, and of whatſoeuer elſe he could ſteale from his mother. The ſame day commeth the ſhepheard, and his miſtris, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of her ſheepe, and the number of her wethers, vnderſtood how her ſonne had ſold ſixe of them, comming in an euening where they were Shee aſked her ſonne, what he had done with the money that he had receiued for the wethers. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he had what to doo therwith, &amp; that he would ſell many mo of them, giuing her ſundry bad words. She takes vp a cudgell to ſtrike him. But he, being wickedly bent, can to her, and did wring it out off her hands. Herevpon, ſhee being very angry, goeth out into the ſtreete to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions that brought him to diſorder, willing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to maintaine her ſonne any more in his lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor to cal him out to go with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth, &amp; to cauſe him ſo fondly to ſpend his money. Her ſon very angry to ſee that his mother had vttered his faults in the open ſtreet, and that before yong maides, who mocked him therewith, hatcheth within his mind a miſche euous imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tempted by the Deuill who watcheth how he may allure vs to yeeld vnto that which may worke our endles wo, ſo poſſeſſed this yong mans mind, that he purpoſed one night to kil his own mother. He vſed to lie in a bed by himſelfe in his mothers chamber. This poore mother being in bed, ſighed much for grief at her ſons ill huſbandry &amp; cariage. He then watcheth &amp; attendeth his time vntil ſhee was a ſteep: &amp; in the end perceiuing her faſt a ſleep, takes a cord, which hee had prepared of purpoſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26311:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->and hauing made a nooſe, hee comming neere his mothers bed, had at firſt ſome remorſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as he was about to put the cord about her neck: but remembring how the day before ſhe had ſhamed him openly, and that before young wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whom he eſteemed more then his mother, this accurſed ſonne, poſſeſſed with the Deuil puts the cord about her necke and ſtrangleth her. And when he ſaw that ſhe had no longer any breath left in her, he hoyſeth her neck vp by the cord, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it faſt to the vpper part of the bedſteed and ſo left her hanging. Then hee takes her keyes, which were vnder the boiſter of her bed, &amp; opens all her cheſts, finding there about two hundred crownes, with rings, borders and other iewels: truſſeth vp altogether, and aſſoone as the Cocke had crowed, he commaunded to haue a horſe ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ryſeth, putteth on his clothes, his boots and ſpurres, and hauing ſhut faſt the chamber doore, where his mother was, goes to horſebacke, and told the man ſeruant that he had appointed with his mother to go to <hi>Chambery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This new <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> or killer of his mother, being on his way, euery ſtep that he ſet forward, ſeemeth to behold burning firebrands before him: feare followed him at the heeles, and a guilty conſcience of that he had done affrighted him: the leaſt noyſe that he heard, was euer and anon as an alarum vnto him, ſo as he knew not which wayes to turne him.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, when the morning was well vp, his mothers maydes, wondring that their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26311:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->miſtreſſe roſe not, knocked at her chamber doore, calling her, but in vaine, for no body anſwered. At length they call in the neighbours, and brea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the doore, and finde the woman there han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. they fetch the Caſtle keeper of the place, and ſtraight way it is ſuſpected to bee her ſonnes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Then he was ſent after in haſt, and beeing knowne all the way he went, was taken at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> and ſo carried ſafe to <hi>Chambery,</hi> where hee freely confeſſed this wicked and horrible fact, and was there condemned by the Senate, to bee pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hed his fleſh off vnder the paps in three places of the towne with pincers red hot, and afterward to be burned to death in the market called <hi>Vernay.</hi> And ſo was he executed on Satterday the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of Auguſt <hi>1606.</hi> At his execution he willed all youth to take example by him, and to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to their fathers and mothers, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of haun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing lewd company. When the fire was burning about him, he cryed vnto God for mercy vntill the laſt gaſpe.</p>
            <p>This may ſerue an example both for parents, to be carefull how they bring vp their children in the feare of God. and in good nurture betimes, while they are vnder their gouernement: and for youth, to take heed that they eſchew riotous and lewd company, leaſt thereby the Deuill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them to the like deſperate and damnable attempts. And ſo God guide vs in the right way.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
